Guide to the Spain Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Original accession
  - Part II, 1505-1891
    - Title: "Dictamen reservado que el Conde de Aranda dió al rey sobre la independencia de las colonias ingleses, después de haber firmado el tratado de paz ajustado en Paris en el año de 1783." Description: Copy, identical to previous entry. NOT FILMED., [ca. 1783] (Box 13, Folder 22, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Memoria secreta presentada al rey Carlos III por el S.E. el Conde de Aranda sobre la independencia de las colonias ingleses después de haber firmado el tratado de Paris de 1783." Description: Copy, identical to previous entry. NOT FILMED., [ca. 1783] (Box 13, Folder 23, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Letter. Place: Havana. Description: Letter in French by Bernardo de Galvez to Mr. Le Cheval de Montaill concerning Louisiana., 1787 August 16 (Box 13, Folder 24, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Report on the Kingdom of Galicia. Description: Report on the Spanish region of Galicia, covering population, migration, agriculture, industry, commerce, economic geography and development issues. ], [ca. 1787 (Box 13, Folder 25, Reel 10U)
    - Author: Ayala, Manuel José de. Title: Índice del diccionario de gobierno y legislación de Indias y España. Place: Madrid. Description: A printed alphabetical index listing of subject headings., 1792 (Box 13, Folder 26, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Letter by the Marquis of Feria. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter from the Marquis of Feria to his brother, José, concerning the death of the Marquis of Valdelirios and other personal matters., 1793 May 25 (Box 13, Folder 27, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Carta del Señor Azara, embajador en Paris al exmo. Señor príncipe de la paz." Place: Barcelona. Description: Handwritten copy of a letter from the Spanish ambassador to France to the prince of Spain concerning Franco-Spanish relations and the ambassador's activities in Paris., 1799 November 26 (Box 13, Folder 28, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Relación de como se entienda los nobles ydalgos y los labradores pecheros del Señorío de Vizcaia y las rentas y y tierras que se le dieron a Juan Zuria por los vizcainos y sus antigüedades el año 773." Description: History which traces the lineage of the occupants of the office. The text also lists the lands and income the Vizcainos (Basques) ceded to Juan Zuria, the first señorío., [17--?] (Box 13, Folder 29, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Índice general de todos los papeles contenidos en los tomos de miscelanea." Description: Handwritten bound volume describing every document found in forty three volumes of miscellaneous papers belonging to Manuel Joséde Ayala, the distinguished Spanish jurist. Many documents deal with the New World., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 30, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Proyecto del establecimiento de un compañía de Indias en España en beneficio evidente del real erario...." Description: Detailed plan for the creation of a new royal trading company so that Spain, rather than other European powers, would profit from its empire. The plan called for dramatically increasing the size of the Spanish navy., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 31, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Tratado de la navegación de Beregeron, Capítulo 23." Description: Portion of a text written by an unidentified [French?] author refuting Spain's claims to exclusive control over the New World., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 32, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Noticia general de el estado de todas las dependencias que incluie la Nueva España y de el desorden conque actualmente subsisten." Description: Brief report dealing with problems facing New Spain at all levels of government. The text also describes the challenges facing the church, the treasury, the army, and the navy., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 33, Reel 10U)
    - Author: Mariana, Juan de. Title: "Discurso de las cosas de la compañía escrito por el Padre Juan de Mariana." Description: An attack on the Society of Jesus (Jesuits) by a member of the order., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 34, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Carta del....Antonio de Monroy....Arzobispo de Santiago, escrita al Marqués de Mejorada en respuesta de los decretos y manifestos que se expedieron en Madrid contra el summo Pontífice el Senor Clemente Undecimo." Description: Letter written by the archbishop of Santiago de Compostela to a member of the Spanish cabinet concerning denunciations of Pope Clement XI emanating from the Spanish court., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 35, Reel 10U)
    - Author: Arias Montaño, Benito? Title: "Monita secreta de los jesuitas"? Description: Handwritten copy of an anti-Jesuit treatise falsely attributed to Montaño, who was a confessor of Philip II of Spain., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 36, Reel 11U)
    - Author: [Ayala, Manuel José de?] Title: Dictionary. Description: Handwritten transcript of dictionary entries (abastos-artilleria) of legal terms. This copy was made in 1849 from the Ayala collection of the Royal Library in Madrid by Domingo del Monte., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 37, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Conducta de la Princesa de los Ursinos en el gavinete del rey cristianisimo en presencia de Madama de Maintenon...." Description: A report about the Princess Ursino, who dominated the Spanish court in the early eighteenth century. The text reviews Spanish affairs at the time and describes the princess's activities., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 38, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Descripción de la corte de Roma." Place: Madrid? Description: Report detailing the composition and duties of officials in the Papal court in Rome., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 39, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Concordia fratrum minorum de observantia cum serenissimo et catholico Rege Ferdinando intia impressa et subscripta a ministro et vicario generalibus, signata sigillis suis sic incipiens." Description: Copy of a document in Latin concerning King Ferdinand of Spain., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 40, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "En la casa real de España los confesores de los reyes...." Place: Madrid? Description: Document describing the history and duties of the confessor to the king of Spain. Also included are lists of the confessors of the kings and queens of Spain., [17--?] (Box 14, Folder 41, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Notarial act. Place: New Orleans. Description: Notarized act of sale of a plantation, located up river from New Orleans, by Eduardo Fortall to Pedro Sauve., 1801 September 19 (Box 14, Folder 42, Reel 11U)
    - Author: Jovellanos, Gaspar de. Title: "Representationes." Place: Mallorca. Description: An appeal to the king of Spain for justice by this well-known figure of the Spanish enlightenment following his arrest and imprisonment., 1801 (Box 14, Folder 43, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Letter and article. Places: Lisbon, Madrid. Description: Copy of a short laudatory letter to the [king of Portugal?] about the restoration of silk factories in Braganza. Also included is a handwritten copy of an article that appeared in the Gazeta de Madrid, with the dateline Paris, about a debate on the French divorce law., 1803 (Box 14, Folder 44, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Suplemento a la orden del día 6 de noviembre del 1805 en la guarnición de Cádiz." Place: Cádiz. Description: Report which describes the French victory at the battle of Caldiero. The text also discusses the battle of Trafalgar in detail. Included are lists of the condition of each Spanish and French ship after Trafalgar, and rosters of dead and wounded Spanish naval officers., 1805 November 6 (Box 14, Folder 45, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Royal order. Place: Aranjuez. Description: Royal order dealing with the establishment of a fund to cover the expenses of the "juzgado de artillería.", 1807 January 22 (Box 14, Folder 46, Reel 11U)
    - Author: Solanos y Noboa, Pasqual. Title: "Acusación contra el gobierno francés." Place: Cádiz? Description: A denunciation of the French government for its invasion of Spain. The accusations are principally based on arguments of natural law., 1808 (Box 15, Folder 47, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Complaint concerning a merchant. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter written by Martin Antonio de Huizi to the count of Cabarras concerning the character of a merchant., 1809 February 10 (Box 15, Folder 48, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Royal decree. Place: Madrid. Description: Printed copy of the royal decree in which the king of Spain re-established the Council of the Indies. Also included are handwritten lists of the council's members and a statement of the body's finances., 1814 (Box 15, Folder 49, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Report on trade with the Americas. Place: Madrid. Description: Report by a Spanish commission concerning the issue of foreign trade with the Americas. The report examines the economic relations other European powers maintained with their colonies, and refutes arguments about Spain's inability to carry on trade with her colonies. The group endorses the restoration of the system of "comercio libre," established in 1778., 1817 July 24 (Box 15, Folder 50, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Sobre la pacificación de América." Place: Madrid. Description: Lengthy defense of Spain's rule of the American colonies, by an unidentified author. The text blames the Americans for the various independence movements in the region; details the virtues of the Spanish imperial system; discusses trade by foreigners with the colonies; and concludes by laying out the bases for imperial trade within the framework of the 1778 decree of "comercio libre.", 1817 (Box 15, Folder 51, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Royal orders. Place: Madrid. Description: A series of handwritten and printed orders by the king of Spain directed to the count of Cartagena. The dispatches deal with royal appointments, political affairs, constitutional reform and military matters; many are on the letterhead of the Ministry of War., 1820 March - October (Box 15, Folder 52, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Diplomatic correspondence. Place: Madrid. Description: Copies of two brief letters exchanged by the French and American ministers to Spain, written in French. Also included is a letter from the papal nuncio to the Spanish minister of state, written in Italian., 1823 (Box 15, Folder 53, Reel 11U)
    - Author: Everett, A. H. Title: Diplomatic note to the king of Spain. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a letter from the American minister to Spain which explains United States policy towards Latin America, and urges the king of Spain to accept the independence of the Latin American colonies. The letter explains how Spain could prosper from increased trade with its former colonies., 1826 January 20 (Box 15, Folder 54, Reel 11U)
    - Author: Everett, A. H. Title: Diplomatic note to the king of Spain. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy, identical to previous entry. NOT FILMED., 1826 January 20 (Box 15, Folder 55, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Letter to Reverendo Alcala. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter to the bishop of Madrid from A. W. Wheeler, requesting a promised letter of introduction, with typescript English summary., 1891 March 30 (Box 15, Folder 56, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Demonstración de la facilidad en los medios para que se efectué la reconquista de América, indicada en los observaciones anteriores." Description: Report, by an unknown author, laying out a plan for the reconquest of Spain's American colonies. The majority of the report deals with how to carry out the plan and how to pay for it., [18--?] (Box 15, Folder 57, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Observaciones sobre los estados de América Española y su restauración." Description: Treatise dealing with the effect which the permanent loss of the American colonies would have on Spain and the means available to the Spanish crown to deal with the situation., [18--?] (Box 15, Folder 58, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Carta al rey del....Fray Juan de Montalvan." Description: Letter from the bishop of Guadix to the king of Spain dealing with problems facing the monarchy., Undated (Box 15, Folder 59, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Report on an earthquake. Place: [Philippines?] Description: Report detailing the damage resulting from an earthquake that occurred on November 30 [no year given] at 8:00 P.M., Undated (Box 15, Folder 60, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Fiestas de ceremonias para el cabildo." Description: List of official days of religious ceremonies observed by the members of the cabildo of an unidentified city., Undated (Box 15, Folder 61, Reel 11U)
    - Title: "Origen de los Agotes." Description: Brief text describing the origins and history of the Agotes, a linage or clan group who lived in Navarre and Aragon., Undated (Box 15, Folder 62, Reel 11U)
    - Title: Miscellaneous index. Description: One page index listing documents from unknown volume., Undated (Box 15, Folder 63, Reel 11U)
  - Duplicating negatives (Box 16)